Hagoromo and Hamura
(ゼツ)母は この地を愛した。
そして人間を愛そうとした。
Mother loved this world.
She tried to love humans.
But her wish was dashed
だが その希望は奪われ→
so she ate the fruit of the Divine Tree
to try to protect her children.
自らの子を守るために
神樹の実を口にした。
However…
しかしだ…。
Mother's real tale of despair
begins from here…
母の本当の絶望の物語は
ここから始まる。
母は それから間もなく
双子を産んだ。
Shortly afterwards,
Mother gave birth to twins.
それが ハゴロモとハムラだ。
They were…Hagoromo and Hamura.
(ハムラ)母上は ああして
毎日 空を見上げているが→
Mother looks up at the sky
like that every day…
いったい何を見ているのだろう。
I wonder what she's looking for?
(ハゴロモ)私たちには
何も語ってくれないからな。
She never tells us anything.
No one knows what's in her heart.
心の内は誰もわからない。
きっと母上には→
Perhaps she has feelings that even we,
her own sons, cannot fathom.
我ら息子とて計り知れない思いが
あるのかもしれぬな。
(ハオリ)
ねぇ ハゴロモ ハムラ ちょっと来て！
Hey, Hagoromo and Hamura!
Please come with me!
どうした ハオリ？
What's the matter, Haori?
てめえのところで
全部 水をとっちまったんじゃ→
If you use all the water at your place,
there won't be any water
downstream for the rice paddies.
下流の田んぼにゃあ
水はいかなくなっちまうだろ！
That's not my fault!
それは俺のせいじゃねえ！
Wait!
What's going on?
待てよ どうしたんだ？
I'll tell ya what's going on!
This guy is taking all the water!
どうもこうも こいつが
水を全部とっちまうからよ。
俺の田んぼが上流にあるんだから
当たり前だろう。
My paddy's upstream,
so I can't help it!
But until now, wasn't there
enough water for everyone?
だけど 今までは他のところにも
水はいってたんだろ？
それが
急に川の流れが弱くなってよ。
Well, all of a sudden,
the flow of the river's gotten weak.
上流で何かあったのか？
Did something happen upstream?
上流を見にいくにも
この山には→
I would go and check,
but there's a huge bear
roaming around this mountain.
どでかい熊がウロウロしてて
うかつには入れねえ。
You gotta be really careful.
この前だって
山菜採りに入った ばあさんが→
Just recently, an old lady went
foraging for edible wild plants,
大ケガさせられたしよ。
and got hurt really bad.
わかった 我々で見てくる。
All right. We'll go check.
Really? That'd be great!
ほんとか？ 助かるよ。
気をつけてね ハゴロモ。
Be careful, Hagoromo.
We'll be fine.
大丈夫だ。 行くぞ ハムラ。
うん。
Let's go, Hamura.
Right.
何か見えるか？
ちょっと待って。
See anything?
Hold on a minute.
(ハムラ)どうやら上流に
でかい岩があるね。
There's a huge boulder upstream.
なるほど こいつが川の流れを
ふさいでたのか。
I see…
So this is what's blocking
the flow of the river.
だけど
この岩は どこから来たんだ？
But where did this boulder
come from?
前に来たときには なかったよ。
It wasn't there the last time
we were up here.
どこからか降ってきたか
誰かが置いたか。
Either it fell from somewhere,
or someone put it there.
誰かって…
こんな大岩を動かせるのは→
What do you bean by "someone"?
No one can move a boulder this big
母上か兄者以外いないぞ。
other than Mother and you,
Elder Brother.
(ガマ丸)
それは わしが置いたのじゃ。
I put it there.
(ガマ丸)お～い 無視するな。
Hey, don't brush me off
like I'm some sort of bug…
じゃが
わしは虫ではなく 蛙じゃがな。
‘Cuz I'm not a bug…
I'm a toad.
おい 私の頭がおかしいのか？
Hey, am I going crazy?
蛙が つまらぬシャレを言っている。
There's a toad trying to
make bad jokes…
兄者… それなら俺も
頭がおかしくなったってことか？
Well, Elder Brother,
it must mean I'm going crazy too.
べつに お前たちの頭は
どうにもなっとらん。
No, you're not going crazy.
I really am talking to you.
ちゃんと わしが話してるんじゃ。
いや… わしのシャレが
おもしろくないという点で→
But if you think my jokes aren't funny,
then that's a little crazy.
おかしいかもしれぬが。
(ハムラ)誰も隠れてない。
No one's hiding around here…
It's not some
Ventriloquism Jutsu either.
腹話術じゃないみたいだ。
You're pretty wary for a human.
用心深いやつじゃの
人間の分際で。
ずいぶんと威張った蛙だな。
You're pretty arrogant for a toad.
We toads have lived here
far longer than you.
お前たちが知らないだけで
わしら蛙のほうが→
ずっと昔から
この地に住んどるんじゃ。
You just don't know it.
A talking toad…
しゃべる蛙って捕まえて帰ったら
みんな喜ぶかな？
You think people will be happy
if we captured it and took it home?
バカ者！ 貴様ら程度に捕まる
わしではない！
Fool!
Do you really think you both
can catch me?
言うじゃないか 蛙のくせに。
For a toad, you sure talk big…
おっ どうやら
新しいお客さんじゃぞ。
It seems we have a guest.
グォ～ッ！
グォ～ グォ～！
グォ～！
That's a huge bear!
でかい熊だな。
Perfect timing.
I'll show you just how strong I am.
ちょうどいい。
わしの強さを自慢してやる。
(ハムラ/ハゴロモ)おぉ～。
この岩はお前たちに会うために
わしが置いたのじゃ。
I placed this boulder here
so I could meet you two.
わしの名前は ガマ丸。
お前たちは ハゴロモとハムラじゃな。
My name is Gamamaru.
And you two are Hagoromo
and Hamura, right?
蛙に呼び捨てにされた。
A toad just addressed us
by our first names…
２人とも ちょっと来い。
Come with me, you two.
おっと 忘れてた。
Oops, I almost forgot.
ほぅ… 少しはやるようじゃな。
Oh…
Not bad.
なんだ？
こんな場所に連れてきて。
Why did you bring us here?
あれを知っているか？
Do you know what that is?
Of course.
もちろん。
あれは 終焉の峠。
That's the Peak of Demise.
あの向こうを見たことはあるか？
Have you ever seen
what's beyond that?
いいや ないな。
No, never.
Mother has warned us
not to go near that peak.
母上からあの峠には近づくな
と言われている。
全員の掟だ。
Everyone must follow that law.
No one has ever seen
what's on the other side.
誰もあの向こう側を
見た者はいない。
The truth behind the Divine Tree
is beyond that peak.
あの向こうに神樹の正体がある。
The truth behind the Divine Tree?
神樹の正体？
(ガマ丸)神樹は大地の力を
吸い取り続けている。
The Divine Tree has been
absorbing the power of this land.
あれがあるかぎり
この大地は弱り続ける。
As long as that tree exists,
the land will continue to weaken.
そうなの？ でも神樹の力で
この地は潤っていると聞くけど。
Is that true?
But I've heard that it's because of
the power of the Divine Tree
that this land has thrived.
違う。 真実を知りたかったら
峠の向こうを見てみるんじゃな。
You're wrong!
If you want to know the truth,
go see what's on the other side
of that peak.
じゃあの。
Later!
真実。
"The truth"?
はぁ？
ほんとにカグヤ様はいないのか？
Is Lady Kaguya really not here?
何度言われても
いないものはいません。
How many times must I tell you?
She's not here.
おかえりなさいまし
ハゴロモ様 ハムラ様。
Welcome home,
Masters Hagoromo and Hamura.
どうした？
このお方がどうにもしつこくて。
What's the matter?
This man is very persistent.
あんた誰？
オイラは旅の薬売りだ。
Who are you?
I'm a traveling medicine peddler.
この辺で商売しようと思って
カグヤ様の許可をもらいに来たのよ。
I wanted to do some business here
and came to get
Lady Kaguya's permission.
母上は？
今晩は留守にされると。
Where is Mother?
She said she would be away tonight.
そうか また出かけたのか。
I see, so she's gone out again.
最近は多いな。
まいったな。
She's been away a lot lately.
What do I do now?
ほぅ… どれどれ？
俺がお前の薬を見てやる。
Well now, what do you have here?
Let me take a look
at your medicines.
うわぁ 人の商売道具に
なにしやがる！
What are you doing to
my products?!
ただの雑草にカビの生えた木の実。
These are just weeds
and moldy nuts…
こりゃ毒キノコだ。
This one's a poisonous mushroom.
If you take these,
you'll get even sicker.
こんなの飲まされたら
よけい具合が悪くなる。
さてはお前 ペテンの薬売りだな？
ギクッ！
You're just a snake oil salesman…
この村には母上と兄者の力がある。
This village has our mother,
my elder brother and me.
それがあれば どんな病気だって
たちどころに治る。
We can cure any illness anywhere,
at anytime.
こんなの買うやつは誰もいないよ。
No one will buy stuff like this.
それって あの神樹様の
お力なのか？
Your power…
Is it from the Divine Tree?
いいから とっとと出ていけ。
痛い目に遭いたくなきゃな！
Just get out of here…
or you'll be sorry.
あ… あ… あぁ～！
チクショー！ バカにしやがって…。
Damn it!
How dare they belittle me!
アタタタタ…。
頭にきたら
腰の痛みが ぶり返してきたぜ。
They made me so mad,
my back pain is flaring up again.
神樹か…。
The Divine Tree, huh?
もし 欠片でも持って帰れば
さぞ お高く…。
If I take even just a small branch,
I could sell it for a fortune…
よし！ 鬼のいぬ間に…。
Yes! While the devil is away…
やめろ やめろ！
うかつに神樹に近づくと 死ぬぞ。
Just forget about it.
Don't be foolish enough
to go near the Divine Tree. You'll die.
あっ！ お前は…。
You are—!
さっきは悪かったな。
弟は ちゃめっ気があるんでな。
I apologize for earlier.
My younger brother
is quite hot-tempered.
何の用だ… あっ！ イテテテ…。
What do you want?!
Oww!
お前に聞きたいことがある。
I want to ask you something.
ふざけるな!!
何も教えてやるものか！
Are you joking?!
You're not getting
anything out of me!
答えてくれれば 腰を治してやる。
If you answer me,
I'll heal your back.
フン！ そんなことで
病気が治ったら 誰も苦労は…。
Like doing that will cure anything.
If it's that simple,
no one would go through…
あ… あれ!? 治った…。
What? The pain's gone?!
おぉ～！ 本当に治ってる。 ハハハ!!
Hey! You really did fix my back!
で… 私の質問に答えてくれるか？
へい！ なんでも。
So, will you answer my questions?
Yes! Anything!
お前は いろいろな場所を
旅してるのだろ？
You've traveled to
many different places, correct?
えぇ そりゃ もう。
それが商売ですから。
Oh, yes.
That's how I make my living.
あの峠の向こうは
見たことがあるか？
Have you ever seen
what's beyond that peak?
あぁ いえ それはないですが
他のところなら…。
No, I haven't.
But I've seen many other lands…
そこでの母上の噂は どんなだ？
What do they say about
my mother in other lands?
へい そりゃ… あぁ え～っと…。
Well, that's…um…
Tell me even if
it's something negative.
言いづらいことでもいい。
へい…。
Okay.
実は カグヤ様が行ってる
神樹へのしきたりに反対して→
There are rumors about people
rebelling here and there,
over Lady Kaguya's
Ritual of the Divine Tree.
あちこちで
反乱が起きてるって噂です。
それを鎮圧するのに カグヤ様は→
And in order to suppress them,
Lady Kaguya has
annihilated the instigators.
彼の国の連中を
全滅させているとか…。
Lately, rumors are swirling that
Lady Kaguya is just a tyrant…
最近じゃ カグヤ様は暴君だって噂が
あちこちで…。
全滅…。
"Annihilated"?
それで 母上は 最近 留守に…。
No wonder Mother has been
away a lot…
行け！ もう 戻ってくるな。
Leave, and never return.
It's for your own good.
そのほうが お前のためだ。
へい。
Yes, sir!
どこも異常ないよ。
Everything is going well.
兄者？
あ… あぁ。
Elder Brother?
Hmm?
Oh good, no news is good news.
何もないのが いちばんだ。
兄者… あの蛙の言ったことが
気になるのかい？
Elder Brother, are you still thinking
about what that toad said?
いや そういうわけではないが…。
No… It's not about that, but…
あれは 神樹様へのしきたりの…。
They're part of the Ritual
of the Divine Tree…
あっ！ そんな…。
あ… 兄者！
No way!
Elder Brother!
ハオリ！
Haori!
ハゴロモ… ハムラ…。
これは…。
Hagoromo…
Hamura…
What's going on?
私に 神樹様への
お使いの知らせが来たの。
I've received notice
to serve the Divine Tree.
But—!
だが…。
しかたないことよ。
I have no choice.
ずっと昔から カグヤ様が決めた
しきたりなんだから…。
This is a ceremony that Lady Kaguya
established eons ago…
ハゴロモ… ハムラ… 短い間だったけど
２人に会えて 楽しかったわ。
Hagoromo, Hamura…
It was only for a short time,
but I'm glad I got to meet you two.
私のこと 忘れないでね。
Please remember me.
ハオリ！
Haori!
母上…。
Mother…
神樹のしきたりを
中止してください。
Please end
the Ritual of the Divine Tree.
(カグヤ)それは ならぬ。
しかし…。
That is not possible.
But—!
お前たちとて わらわに
逆らうことは許しません。
I will not tolerate any defiance,
even if you are my sons.
では 教えてください。
Then please tell me…
What happens to those who go to
the Divine Tree as part of this ritual?
あのしきたりで
神樹に向かった者たちは→
どうなるのです？ なぜ
１人も帰ってこないのですか？
Why does no one ever return?
しきたりは必要なのだ。
あの者たちが来るまでは。
This ritual is necessary…
until the others arrive.
"The others"?
あの者たち？
それはまだ
お前たちが知る必要はない。
You don't need to know
about them just yet.
Hagoromo, Hamura…
I am leaving once more.
ハゴロモ ハムラ わらわはまた出かける。
留守を頼む。
はい。
Take care of things in my absence.
Yes.
兄者 まさか…。
Elder Brother…
You're not thinking of…
ああ 私はあの峠に登ろうと思う。
Yes, I intend to climb that peak.
母上に知れれば
ただでは済まないぞ。
If Mother finds out, you'll get
into a great deal of trouble.
それは覚悟のうえだ。
I'm prepared for the consequences.
わかった 兄者 俺も行こう。
Okay, Elder Brother.
I'm coming with you.
何だ これは？
What is this?!
兄者！
Elder Brother!
ハムラ。
Hamura!
どうした？
兄者 この繭を。
What's wrong?
Elder Brother!
Can you deal with this cocoon?
ハオリ！
Haori!
ハオリ 起きろ ハオリ。
Haori! Wake up, Haori!
兄者 ムダだ。
Elder Brother…
It's no use…
死んでる。
She's dead.
うぉ～ うぉ～！
(ハムラ)これが
神樹のしきたりの正体。
So this is…the truth behind
the Ritual of the Divine Tree.
(ハムラ)兄者 その目は…。
Elder Brother! Your eyes!
出てこい ガマ丸。
Come out, Gamamaru!
どうやら行ったようじゃな
あの峠の向こうに。
It seems like you went
beyond that peak…
わしに ついてこい。
Come with me.
ここは？
Where are we?
ここは蝦蟇の国じゃ。
This is the Land of Toads.
なんだ？ 不思議な力を感じる。
What is this…strange power I feel?
ほう さすがじゃな
人間でここの力を感じとるとは。
Oh… I'm impressed that a human
can feel the power here.
ここは仙力と呼ばれる
自然パワーが満ちておる。
The natural power known as
Sage Power flows freely here.
だから その力を使えば…。
And so, if you use this power…
よっ！ わしにでも
こんなことができるのじゃ。
Even I can do something like this.
すげえ。
よいしょ ついてこい。
Wow…
Follow me!
これは記憶石と呼ばれるものじゃ。
This is known as the Memory Stone.
記憶石？
"Memory Stone"?
地上に起きた あらゆることを
記録している石じゃ。
Everything that occurs aboveground
is recorded in this stone…
見るがいい
かつて 何が起きたのかを。
Look at what happened in the past…
その昔 あの樹は
空から降ってきた。
Long ago, that tree fell
from the sky…
それを追うように
お前たちの母 カグヤもやってきた。
And, as if in pursuit, your mother
Kaguya appeared here.
カグヤは地上に降りてから
この地の帝と恋に落ち→
And when your mother arrived,
she fell in love with
the emperor of this land
お前たちを身ごもった。
and she became pregnant with you.
だが カグヤの運命は
人間に翻弄され→
However,
Kaguya's destiny with humans
was to be trifled by them
そして 人間の敵に回った。
and in the end,
she became their enemy.
カグヤは 神樹の力を得て
お前たちの父親を→
Kaguya acquired the power
of the Divine Tree,
and your father,
along with his people,
そして 人々を
神樹の生贄に変えた。
were sacrificed to it.
一部の人間は
人間を絶やさぬために→
But, to make sure
mankind didn't perish,
she revived some of the humans,
記憶を抜かれ
元に戻されたようじゃがな。
erased their memories
and put them back.
真相は カグヤしか知らぬ。
Only Kaguya knows the truth.
母上は いったいどこから？
なぜ神樹を守ろうとする？
Where is Mother from anyway?
Why does she protect
the Divine Tree?
わからん。
遠い空からやってきたことと→
I don't know.
Perhaps it's related to the fact that
she appeared from far up in the sky.
関係しているのかもしれぬ
はっきりしていることは…。
One thing is clear…
あの神樹が生えてから→
Since the Divine Tree took root,
明らかに大地の自然エネルギ-は
減少しているということじゃ。
the Nature Energy of this land
is being depleted.
なんてことを。
How could that happen?
大地ばかりではない
人間からもじゃ。
Not just from the land…
but from humans too.
あの神樹がある限り
やがて大地は枯れ果て→
As long as that Divine Tree exists…
this great land will wither,
and we will suffer the same fate.
我々も同じ運命をたどる。
母上と
話をする必要があるな。
We must speak with mother.
だけど母上が話なんて…。
Will she even listen to us?
ハゴロモよ お前の母の力は絶大じゃ。
Hagoromo,
your mother's power is immense.
わしも素直に話を
聞いてくれる相手とは思えない。
I doubt that you can
confront her directly.
たとえ息子のお前でも。
Even if you are her son.
ガマ丸 私に仙力の使い方を
教えてくれないか。
Gamamaru, will you teach me
how to use Sage Power?
兄者 まさか母上と
戦うつもりでは？
Elder Brother!
You're not planning to fight Mother,
are you?!
万が一のためだ。
It's just in case…
なるほど カグヤの力を
強く受け継いだお前が→
I see…
If you, who inherited Kaguya's power,
acquire Sage Power…
仙力を習得すれば たしかに
対抗できるかもしれぬ。
you could definitely take her on.
じゃが。
なんだ？
– However…
– What is it?
お前に
仙力を教えることは→
Teaching you Sage Power
is very risky.
危険な賭けじゃ。
なぜだ？
Why is that?
仙力を会得したお前が→
Is there any guarantee that
after acquiring Sage Power,
母親と同じにならない保証が
あるか？
you won't become the same
as your mother?
ガマ丸 ここまできて→
Gamamaru… After coming this far,
have you become scared?
怖気づいたのか？
なんじゃと？
What did you say?
お前の話は矛盾している。
You're contradicting yourself.
お前は
なぜ私たちを待っていた？
Why did you lie in wait for us, then?
お前は母上と我々が戦うことを
最初から予測していたはずだ。
You planned to pit us against Mother
and make us fight from the very start.
う… お前 人間のクセに鋭いな。
You're pretty shrewd for a human,
aren't you?
そうじゃ
お告げがあったのじゃ。
Yes, I had a revelation.
(ハゴロモ)お告げ？
夢じゃ。
Revelation?
Yes, a dream.
Toads rarely, if ever, dream.
ガマは滅多に夢を見ない。
その夢は いわば予言に近い。
But that dream was
more like a prophecy…
わしはお前たちが
カグヤと戦う夢を見た。
I dreamed of you battling Kaguya.
その結果は？
How did it end?
そこまでは
見ていないはずだ。
I don't think his dream
went that far.
見ていたら
びびりなどしない。
If it did,
he wouldn't be so nervous.
ゲコ!? 何から何まで
蛙の心を読むとは。
Wha—?! How can you see so far
into a toad's heart so clearly…
なんてやつじゃ。
Just who are you?
何も考えるな。
Clear your mind…
自然エネルギーを感じて
それを自分の中に取り込め。
Just feel the Nature Energy
and take it into yourself.
《こいつは驚きだのお。
He's a surprise…
ハゴロモめ あっという間に
仙力を習得しとる》
Hagoromo's acquired Sage Power
in no time at all.
母上
もうお戻りになられたのですか？
Mother!
You're back so soon…
ハゴロモは どうしたのです？
Where is Hagoromo?
兄者は まだ村を
見回りに行ったまま。
Elder Brother is still out
patrolling the village…
ハムラ。
Hamura!
わらわに隠し事は無駄だ。
Hiding things from me is useless.
う！
無駄だ。
It's useless…even if you try to
repel me with your Byakugan…
お前の白眼で
跳ね返そうとしても→
わらわの白眼は
お前のを はるかに上回る。
My Byakugan is far more
superior to yours.
You two broke the law,
and went to the peak, didn't you?
Hiding things from me is useless.
I can read your thoughts
and feelings.
Then why?
You must know why we're
angry with you, Mother.
It seems that you were in love
with that young girl…
Next time on